Hi, I'm
Maria Garay, and I'm a PhD student
at the University of Salamanca in Spain.
And what I'm going to talk about here
is part of my PhD,
which in general— as a general project,
aims to look
at the aesthetics
and politics of code poetry.
I don't want to get too much
into classifications,
but my focus on code poetry
is specifically in that which is written
in programing languages, whose text
is made up of syntactically correct
and potentially executable code,
and whether it produces an output or not.
But for the sake of clarity,
things like [?]
and some of Jodi's works
would be, for example,
outside of the scope of my research.
And what I'm going to talk about
is also quite different
to what I initially proposed,
because recently I've come into an avenue
of looking at the relationship
between code poetry and labor that
I thought would be more exciting
to explore here.
One of the tasks
that I've been addressing
recently in my PhD
has been that of seeing
how code poetry integrates
into the wider genealogies of poetry.
And it turns out that this integration
is also deeply linked with labor.
There are two instances
that I will pinpoint today
to approach this relationship.
One kind of in the most recent history
related to code poetry,
and then another one looking further back
into the origins of poetry
and how both of these
are connected through the idea of labor.
So the first
instance that I wanted to look at
is the seed of code poetry as a genre,
which I trace back to “Just another Perl
hacker” program.
And here.
So I work in Spain,
and I've never heard the acronym for “Just
another Perl hacker”
pronounced in English.
So if I completely made up
the pronunciation of this acronym,
please feel free to let me know.
I've been calling it “japes.”
I don't know if that's right.
But, yeah,
“japes.” Short programs
whose only function
is to print the sentence “Just
another Perl hacker” into a console.
And just in case
this is not familiar to everyone,
they became really popular amongst
Perl programmers to use as signatures
and emails or online forums
when Perl came into use.
And “Just another Perl hacker” programs,
they have to be brief enough
to fit a signature.
And they tend to consist of creatively
obfuscated code,
so they are formally quite constrained.
This premise is really simple,
but precisely because of that,
when you look at the village of “japes”
that ended up being produced, you find a
really wide
scope of experiments
which are really similar
to those in concrete
poetry and European constraint literature.
For example,
you get “japes” that only use characters
that don't exceed their writing line,
so that don't go either
above or under kind of their, their line.
This was itself a constraint
proposed by members of the Oulipo
when they imagined a man that had access
to very little paper,
and that in order to maximize the—
optimize
the amount of space that they were using,
they could only use characters
that didn't go above or below,
and someone re-imagined this constraint
in Perl.
For example, there are “japes”
that only use— that are written only
using punctuation, or there are others
in which the code itself is ASCII art.
So it's a mix of things
that were happening
already in concrete poetry and Oulipian
literature that kind of end up
bleeding into
what people were doing with “japes.”
And the reason I'm going to “japes”
is because these already
look or like, feel like
proto code poems, right?
Or not
even proto, just like proper code poems.
But as a genre, the first code poem
that is recognized as such
is this famous haiku by Larry Wall.
Which was produced
as a dare to him, or was proposed
as a dare to him by Sharon Hopkins.
And then she was kind of the one that took
it further and became the catalyst
for a lot more Perl poetry being made.
She kind of popularized the genre,
and that's why this one is considered
the first one, I would say,
although that's a bit nebulous.
But the reason why “japes” seem special
is because they gave programmers
a form in which the code that they wrote
had the explicit role of being read.
This wasn't kind of a secondary thing
to their function,
but it was because the function was given
for all of them.
They all just had to produce to print
“Just another Perl hacker” into a console.
Then the focus was put elsewhere.
The important part is what
the code itself looks like, and that it—
and that they serve
as kind of a personal signature style.
It's code made explicitly to be seen
and to be recognized
as someone's artwork.
With this story, I want to make
that most recent connection with labor,
and that is that code poetry stems
not from poets or artists
that were looking to express themselves
in a new medium and then arrived to code,
but rather from workers of code
that being intimately acquainted
with their material, began using it for
aesthetic and playful and ludic
means beyond code’s executable function.
So we can see here how code poetry happens
as an excess of work.
And this is the idea that kind of gives
name to what— my talk today.
That's kind of half of the story.
And then the other story
that I have been focusing on recently
and that I established
a bit of a tentative parallelism
with the one I've just told
is a much more older one.
In when when understanding
how code poetry is part
of a longer
literary history, I have ended up looking
to much
more ancient times that I had predicted,
and have ended up turning to the pre
literate and prehistorical origins
of poetry itself,
which seems a bit excessive,
a bit of a stretch, but surprisingly,
this is where it has taken me.
And I will try to explain
how both histories echo each other.
The one of code poetry
and then poetry in general.
I arrived at this
because there's a Marxist literary
critic called George Thomson,
who in the mid 20th century suggested
that there is a strict link between labor
and the emergence of poetry.
His hypothesis was that
when hominids were learning
to use heavy tools
and trying to coordinate collective labor,
they kind of reflexively emitted
these rhythmic and repetitive grunts.
So everyone was lifting these heavy things
and at the same time,
and needed this coordinating apparatus.
And as the use of tools is perfected,
these sounds become more articulate,
but they also become unnecessary
because they no longer need
this sonorous apparatus to coordinate it.
But he says that this
sound structure survives in
the rituals, then performed as a rehearsal
for a task carried out.
So when when the sound doesn't
directly accompany the task, it
branches out to become a mimetic dance
that prepares people
for the— for a successful reality.
So the rituals have a function
akin to magic.
It is performed in order to
improve the task that is going to happen
by some symbolic link between the dance
and the task itself.
So Thomson's theory
is that formally patterned poetic
speech is born out of work with tools,
and the idea that you can effect reality
with incantation the same way you
can effect it with a manufactured tool.
This is a beautiful proposal, of course,
but it remains hypothetical
and also written in 1945.
But more recent studies,
like Christopher Collins’s “Paleopoetics,”
show that word and tool
do actually come together in ritual,
and that in that form, speech
becomes a similar artifact to the tool.
So he makes the comparison between
conversational speech and poetic speech
in the sense that a conversational speech
works as a found tool.
So the way you would find a stick
and maybe use it for a bit on your walk
through— on your hike
through the mountains,
but then discard it, versus
how poetic speech
becomes an artifact
that you keep and reuse.
And that sticks
the same way when you make a knife,
you're not going to throw it out.
You're going to keep it
because it's useful again and again.
So in these manufactured artifacts
that are poetic
objects, rhythm and repetition
are preserved as characteristics
of their kind of speech.
And in being performed again and again
as rituals,
these form into formal patterns and become
more structured as they get repeated.
So from this kind of second, more ancient
story of the prehistory of poetry,
I want to derive the idea
that in many ways, poetry is born
out of an act that aspires to be
executable, so that poetry has always
did aspire to be a bit of a program
that can effect reality
the same way at all— does.
The history of executable speech
and the idea that symbols
can be transmuted into action
is well known and really long.
For example, Florian Cramer
retells a quite comprehensive
kind of catalog of this story in his book
Words Made Flesh.
So it's not really that
what I'm saying here is new at all,
but my aim is to orient
the understanding of the origins of code
poetry as an excess born
out of the peripheries of labor
that kind of turn to aesthetic purposes,
non instrumental, nonfunctional aesthetic
purposes, and also to show how this echoes
the origins of poetry itself,
that executable speech stands out
of the desire to work, to change reality.
And from it we get the formal patterning
that historically governs
poetic speech and that code,
which is the executable
speech of today—
executable texts of today.
Although—
well, I'm not going to get into that.
But code that the executed—
as the executable text of today
that does effect reality further
than a change in attitude towards the task
they effect.
Physical reality also produces its own
excess, its own code
with poetic intention
that follows formal patterns
beyond functional ones.
I hope I stuck to time.
This is kind of the summary of my point.
I hope that makes sense.